<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:r="http://www.rsuitecms.com/rsuite/ns/metadata" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" r:rsuiteId="972260" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jbjsam</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Bone Joint Surg Am</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Journal of Bone &amp; Joint Surgery</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9355</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1535-1386</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Inc.</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta r:rsuiteId="972261">
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.E.00469</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Scientific Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>0070</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Influence of Acetabular Coverage on Hip Survival After Free Vascularized Fibular Grafting for Femoral Head Osteonecrosis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Roush</surname>
<given-names>Thomas F.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>Steven A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Pietrobon</surname>
<given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Braga</surname>
<given-names>Larissa</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Urbaniak</surname>
<given-names>James R.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Duke University Medical Center, Box 3000, Durham, NC 27710. E-mail address: <email>roush003@mc.duke.edu</email></aff>
<aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Duke University Medical Center, Box 3389, Durham, NC 27710. E-mail address: <email>olson016@mc.duke.edu</email></aff>
<aff id="A3"><label>3</label> Center for Excellence in Surgical Outcomes, Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Duke University Medical Center, Box 3094, Durham, NC 27710. E-mail address: <email>pietr007@mc.duke.edu</email></aff>
<aff id="A4"><label>4</label> Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, CB 7400, Chapel Hill, NC 27599-7400. E-mail address: <email>braga@email.unc.edu</email></aff>
<aff id="A5"><label>5</label> Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Duke University Medical Center, Box 2912, Durham, NC 27710. E-mail address: <email>urban006@mc.duke.edu</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2006</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>88</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>2152</fpage>
<lpage>2158</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2006 by The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Incorporated</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="JBJA088102152.pdf" xlink:title="pdf"/>
<abstract>
<p id="P1"><bold>Background:</bold> Osteonecrosis of the femoral head frequently results in collapse of the head and subsequent arthrosis of the joint. Surgical treatment has been based entirely on the evaluation of the femoral side of the hip joint, with little consideration given to the possible influence on outcome of the orientation of the acetabulum.</p>
<p id="P2"><bold>Methods:</bold> We retrospectively reviewed a consecutive series of 200 hips in 160 patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head who had undergone free vascularized fibular grafting between 1997 and 1998. The mean duration of clinical follow-up was 7.5 years. Ninety-one hips in seventy-one patients were evaluated radiographically for evidence of progression of femoral head collapse at a minimum of two years, and a mean of three years, postoperatively. We defined conversion to a total hip arthroplasty and progression of femoral head collapse as the failure end points, and we analyzed the association of the acetabular center-edge angle of Wiberg, the area and laterality of the lesion, the amount of preoperative collapse of the femoral head, and the etiology of the osteonecrosis with the likelihood of failure.</p>
<p id="P3"><bold>Results:</bold> Forty-eight (24%) of the 200 hips had undergone conversion to a total hip arthroplasty at the time of the final clinical follow-up. In addition, 15% (fourteen) of the ninety-one hips with sufficient radiographic follow-up demonstrated progression of femoral head collapse at the time of the final radiographic examination. Of the hips with a center-edge angle of ≤30°, 55% (of those with sufficient radiographic follow-up) demonstrated progressive collapse and 45% were converted to a total hip arthroplasty. In contrast, of the hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;30°, 10% had progressive collapse (p = 0.002) and 6% were converted to a total hip arthroplasty (p &lt; 0.001). Neither the etiology nor the size of the lesion was significantly correlated with progression of collapse or conversion to a total hip arthroplasty.</p>
<p id="P4"><bold>Conclusions:</bold> Patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head and a suboptimal center-edge angle of the hip are at substantial risk for progression of femoral head collapse and conversion to a total hip arthroplasty following free vascularized fibular grafting. An estimation of the degree of hip dysplasia should be included in the preoperative assessment of patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head for prognostic and possibly surgical planning purposes.</p>
<p id="P5"><bold>Level of Evidence:</bold> Therapeutic <underline>Level IV</underline>. See Instructions to Authors for a complete description of levels of evidence.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1">
<title/>
<p id="P6">The outcomes of surgical treatment of osteonecrosis of the femoral head have been shown to be influenced by factors such as etiology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>, stage of disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, size of the lesion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>, and location<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> of the lesion. As the primary pathologic focus of the disease is the femoral head, none of the most commonly used classification systems (those described by Ficat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>, Steinberg et al. [University of Pennsylvania]<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, Marcus et al. [University of Florida]<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>, Association Research Circulation Osseous [ARCO]<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>, and Urbaniak [Duke University]<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>) include evaluation of the acetabulum, with the exception of arthrosis of the hip joint. Yet, the orientation of the acetabulum influences the contact stresses about the hip joint<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>.</p>
<p id="P7">We hypothesized that patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head and less than optimal acetabular coverage experience higher stresses of the femoral head, as seen in patients with developmental dysplasia of the hip, and therefore have a higher prevalence of failure when treated with a femoral head-preserving procedure such as free vascularized fibular grafting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p id="P8">Between March 1997 and December 1998, 160 consecutive patients (200 hips) underwent free vascularized fibular grafting for the treatment of predegenerative osteonecrosis (Steinberg stage IVC or less) at our center. Because of the wide geographic diversity of the patients referred to our center, the overwhelming majority were not reevaluated by the treating surgeon following discharge from the hospital. Rather, the referring orthopaedic surgeon who provided follow-up care sent follow-up radiographs to us and informed us whether the hip had been converted to a total hip arthroplasty.</p>
<p id="P9">After our institutional review board granted us approval to proceed with the study, preoperative, immediate postoperative, and available final follow-up anteroposterior pelvic radiographs were evaluated. The only postoperative clinical information that we requested from the referring surgeon was whether or not the hip had been converted to a total hip arthroplasty. In addition, we contacted each patient to inquire whether the hip had been converted to a total hip arthroplasty. We did not use a validated outcomes assessment system to evaluate other aspects of the clinical status of the patients. The status of the hip with regard to whether it had been converted to a total hip arthroplasty was known for 160 patients (200 hips), for whom the mean duration of clinical follow-up was 7.5 years (range, 6.6 to 8.3 years). We were able to evaluate the postoperative radiographs of seventy-one patients (ninetyone hips) in this group, at a mean of three years (range, two to five years) postoperatively.</p>
<p id="P10">There were 111 male patients (141 hips; 70.5%) and forty-nine female patients (fifty-nine hips; 29.5%). The osteonecrosis of the femoral head involved ninety-eight left hips and 102 right hips. The average age at the time of surgery was 33.6 years (range, fifteen to forty-eight years). Preoperatively, seventy hips had no collapse, seventy-six had 1 mm of collapse, forty-three had 2 mm of collapse, and eleven had 3 mm of collapse.</p>
<p id="P11">The contributory etiology of the osteonecrosis of the femoral head was steroid use in eighty-three hips, idiopathic in forty-nine, alcohol abuse in forty-one, traumatic in twenty, and another cause in seven (chemotherapy, pregnancy, and slipped capital femoral epiphysis in two each and sickle-cell disease in one).</p>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Radiographic Evaluation</title>
<p id="P12">For the radiographic evaluation, we used a modification of the Steinberg classification system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, which includes measurements of lesion size and quantifies the amount of femoral head collapse.</p>
<p id="P13">Preoperatively, the area (length × width) of each necrotic lesion was measured on an anteroposterior pelvic radiograph after comparing it with a preoperative magnetic resonance imaging scan to better appreciate the extent of the lesion. At the time of final follow-up, radiographic measurements were made on an anteroposterior pelvic radiograph and compared with those made on the preoperative anteroposterior radiograph. Each lesion had been assessed at the initial encounter with the patient by the senior one of us (J.R.U.) and had been qualitatively graded as A when it involved &lt;25% of the femoral head, B when it involved 25% to 50%, and C when it involved &gt;50%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. According to this assessment, there were thirty-one Grade-A lesions, 102 Grade-B lesions, and sixty-seven Grade-C lesions (see Appendix). According to the classification system of Steinberg et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, there were twenty-six Grade-A lesions, ninety-eight Grade-B lesions, and seventy-six Grade-C lesions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>TABLE I</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of Hips According to Classification System of Steinberg et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Stage/Size</td>
<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">No. of Hips</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0 (not applicable)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">I (normal radiographic findings, positive findings on magnetic resonance image)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">II (cystic and sclerotic changes)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    A (&lt;15%)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    B (15%-30%)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    C (&gt;30%)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">III (crescent sign)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    A (&lt;15%)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    B (15%-30%)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    C (&gt;30%)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">IV (partial collapse)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    A (&lt;15% and &lt;2 mm depression)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    B (15%-30% or 2-4 mm depression)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">    C (&gt;30% or &gt;4 mm depression)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">V (joint space narrowing)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">VI (end-stage arthrosis)</td>
<td align="right" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p id="P14">A concentric template was used to measure femoral head flattening, linear collapse, or articular step-off on the preoperative anteroposterior pelvic radiographs. The magnitude of femoral head asphericity was recorded in millimeters and ranged from 0 (spherical) to 3 mm of asphericity. Although not part of the grading system, we recorded the horizontal distance between vertical lines drawn at the most lateral aspects of the avascular lesion and the acetabulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). A negative value denotes that the lateral edge of the lesion is lateral to the lateral edge of the acetabulum. We also determined the center-edge angle of Wiberg<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> on the preoperative and final postoperative anteroposterior pelvic radiographs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Surgical Technique</title>
<p id="P15">The surgical procedure has remained essentially unchanged since the publication of our original reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. Postoperatively, the patients remained non-weight-bearing using crutches for six weeks, after which they progressed to full weight-bearing as tolerated. Full weight-bearing was achieved by all patients by six months.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>Survivorship Analysis</title>
<p id="P16">We defined two end points—progression of femoral head collapse and conversion to a total hip arthroplasty—for the survivorship analyses.</p>
<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Fig. 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Anteroposterior pelvic radiograph showing assessment of the laterality of the osteonecrotic lesion of the right hip. Two vertical lines were drawn perpendicular to a line connecting the inferiormost extent of the ischial tuberosities; the first line was drawn through the lateral margin of the acetabulum, and the second was drawn parallel to it and through the most lateral aspect of the avascular lesion. The figure demonstrates a lesion-acetabular edge distance of –3 mm; this negative value denotes that the lateral edge of the lesion is lateral to the lateral edge of the acetabulum. We hypothesized that avascular lesions approaching or exceeding the lateral edge of the acetabulum would be the most prone to collapse.</p>
</caption>
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="JBJA0881021520G01"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p id="P17">Statistical analysis was performed with Intercooled Stata 8.0 software (Stata, College Station, Texas). Descriptive analysis was conducted with use of means and standard deviations for continuously distributed variables and frequencies or proportions for categorical variables. Each variable was evaluated with respect to the categorical outcome and to each of the other variables. Since femoral head coverage presented a normal distribution, its association with the categorical outcomes was measured with use of t tests. Crude comparisons between hips with a center-edge angle of ≤30° or &gt;30° and the prevalence of conversion to a total hip arthroplasty were evaluated with use of log-rank tests and Kaplan-Meier plots. The risk-adjusted association between femoral head coverage and final progression to collapse or to a total hip arthroplasty was measured with use of logistic models. Finally, Cox proportional models were used to evaluate the risk-adjusted association between head coverage and the time to total hip arthroplasty.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S7">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Univariate Analysis</title>
<p id="P18">Forty-eight (24%) of the 200 hips were converted to a total hip arthroplasty. Thirty-one (65%) of the forty-eight total hip arthroplasties were performed at our center, and the remaining seventeen (35%) were performed either by the referring surgeon or by his or her designee. At the time of this study, no patient was awaiting a total hip arthroplasty.</p>
<p id="P19">The average time to conversion to a total hip arthroplasty was twenty-six months (range, five to seventy-two months). An additional fourteen hips (thirteen patients) with a minimum of two years of radiographic follow-up demonstrated progression of collapse on the final follow-up anteroposterior pelvic radiographs. Thus, sixty-two hips in fifty-six patients demonstrated either progression of collapse or had undergone a total hip arthroplasty during the follow-up interval. This represented 31% of all hips in the series.</p>
<p id="P20">The average size of the necrotic lesions was 31 × 17 mm (range, 5 × 6 mm to 50 × 39 mm). The mean distance from the vertical line denoting the lateral edge of the lesion to the vertical line projected from the lateral edge of the acetabulum was 3 mm (range, –17 to 25 mm). The mean center-edge angle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> was 30° (range, –2° to 48°).</p>
<p id="P21">With the numbers studied, the etiology of the osteonecrosis did not significantly portend final progression of collapse or conversion to a total hip arthroplasty.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>Bivariate Analysis</title>
<p id="P22">Hips with progression of collapse had a mean center-edge angle of 24° (range, 18° to 36°), and those without progression of collapse had a mean center-edge angle of 32° (range, 20° to 45°) (p &lt; 0.001). Similarly, hips that were converted to a total hip arthroplasty had a mean center-edge angle of 25° (range, 9° to 39°), whereas those that did not require additional surgery had a mean center-edge angle of 30° (range, 2° to 48°) (p &lt; 0.001).</p>
<p id="P23">Of the forty-three hips that were followed radiographically for at least two years and had not had a total hip arthroplasty, those with a center-edge angle of ≤25° had a 69% rate (nine of thirteen) of progression of collapse. In contrast, hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;25° had a 17% rate (five of thirty) of progression of collapse. This difference was significant (p &lt; 0.001). Of the entire series of 200 hips, those with a center-edge angle of ≤25° had a 52% rate (thirty-one of sixty) of conversion to a total hip arthroplasty, whereas those with a centeredge angle of &gt;25° had a 12% rate (seventeen of 140) of conversion to a total hip arthroplasty (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). This difference was also significant (p &lt; 0.001).</p>
<p id="P24">When compared with hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;25°, hips with a center-edge angle of ≤25° were eleven times more likely to demonstrate progression of collapse and seven times more likely to undergo conversion to a total hip arthroplasty as determined by odds ratio calculation.</p>
<p id="P25">Of the forty-three hips that were followed radiographically for at least two years and had not had a total hip arthroplasty, those with a center-edge angle of ≤30° demonstrated a rate of progressive collapse of 55% (twelve of twenty-two). In contrast, hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;30° had a rate of progressive collapse of 10% (two of twenty-one). This difference was significant (p = 0.002). Of the entire series of 200 hips, those with a center-edge angle of ≤30° had a 45% rate (forty-one of ninety-two) of conversion to a total hip arthroplasty, whereas those with a center-edge angle of &gt;30° had a 6% rate (seven of 108) of conversion to a total hip arthroplasty. This difference was also significant (p &lt; 0.001).</p>
<fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Fig. 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of hips with progression of collapse or conversion to a total hip arthroplasty according to the center-edge (CE) angle.</p>
</caption>
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="JBJA0881021520G02"/>
</fig>
<p id="P26">When compared with hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;30°, hips with a center-edge angle of ≤30° were eleven times more likely to demonstrate progression of collapse and ten times more likely to undergo conversion to a total hip arthroplasty.</p>
<p id="P27">The mean area of lesions with eventual progression of collapse was 741 mm<sup>2</sup> (range, 150 to 2200 mm<sup>2</sup>), whereas the mean area of lesions without progression of collapse was 553 mm<sup>2</sup> (range, 98 to 1569 mm<sup>2</sup>). The mean area of lesions in hips that eventually underwent total hip arthroplasty was 658 mm<sup>2</sup> (range, 150 to 1785 mm<sup>2</sup>), whereas the mean area of lesions in hips that did not undergo total hip arthroplasty was 556 mm<sup>2</sup> (range, 30 to 2200 mm<sup>2</sup>). With the numbers studied, these differences were not significant.</p>
<p id="P28">The distance of the most lateral aspect of the lesion from the lateral edge of the acetabulum on the anteroposterior pelvic radiograph was significantly inversely correlated with progression of collapse, although not with conversion to a total hip arthroplasty. The mean distance in the hips with progression of collapse was 0 mm (range, –17 to 20 mm), whereas the mean distance in the hips without progression of collapse was 4 mm (range, –10 to 12 mm) (p = 0.047). The mean distance in the hips that eventually underwent a total hip arthroplasty was 2 mm (range, –17 to 13 mm), whereas the mean distance in the hips that did not undergo conversion to a total hip arthroplasty was 3 mm (range, –15 to 25 mm) (p = 0.128). No significant correlation between the mean distance and the center-edge angle was apparent.</p>
<p id="P29">Kaplan-Meier analysis predicted a seventy-month (5.8-year) rate of survival (no progression of collapse or conversion to a total hip arthroplasty) of 55% for hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;25° and of 0% for hips with a center-edge angle of ≤25° (p <italic>&lt;</italic> 0.005). More strikingly, Kaplan-Meier analysis predicted a seventy-six-month (6.3-year) rate of survival of 70% for hips with a center-edge angle of &gt;30° and of 0% for hips with a center-edge angle of ≤30° (p <italic>=</italic> 0.007) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S10">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="P30">Although osteonecrosis of the femoral head is primarily a disease confined to the femoral head, the results of this study suggest that the orientation of the acetabulum is an important determinant of the prognosis. To our knowledge, this study represents the first evaluation of acetabular coverage as a prognostic factor in the outcomes of the surgical treatment of this disease. We found lower center-edge angles to be strongly correlated with adverse outcomes, as evidenced by either progression of the femoral head collapse or conversion to a total hip arthroplasty. An explanation of this finding can be inferred from the work of Hadley et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> and others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>, who emphasized the presence of cumulative high articular contact stresses in hips with developmental dysplasia. In our study, 65% of the hips demonstrated at least 1 mm of collapse preoperatively. We have noted that even 1 mm of collapse of the femoral head seen on radiographs is associated with some macroscopic abnormalities of the articular cartilage seen intraoperatively. Thus, an already structurally compromised articular surface in the setting of increased contact stresses secondary to developmental dysplasia of the hip might increase the risk of further collapse or failure.</p>
<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
<label>Fig. 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Kaplan-Meier survivorship estimates (with 95% confidence intervals) comparing hips that had a center-edge (CE) angle of ≤30° with hips that had an angle of &gt;30°. The difference between the survivorship estimates was significant (p = 0.007).</p>
</caption>
<graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="JBJA0881021520G03"/>
</fig>
<p id="P31">That a dysplastic acetabulum might be an independent risk factor for a poorer prognosis in patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head is not a novel concept. Gregosiewicz and Wosko<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> examined 254 hips with congenital dislocation in children who had been treated conservatively and noted that severe osteonecrosis of the femoral head occurred twice as frequently in hips with a dysplastic acetabulum.</p>
<p id="P32">Historically, varus, valgus, flexion, and rotational proximal femoral osteotomies have been proposed to move the avascular lesion of the femoral head away from the weight-bearing surface<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. More recently, a curved intertrochanteric varus osteotomy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> and a proximal femoral osteotomy combined with free vascularized fibular grafting have been reported for treatment of osteonecrosis of the femoral head caused by nonunion of the femoral neck<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. The threshold, however, for eligibility for these procedures has been proposed to be less than a 200° arc of necrosis, as measured as a combination of the arcs on combined anteroposterior and lateral hip radiographs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. For comparative purposes, it should be noted that 174 (87%) of the 200 hips in our series had an arc of necrosis of &lt;200°. Results of isolated proximal femoral osteotomies have demonstrated widely variable success rates depending on follow-up time, size of the lesion, and stage of the disease at the time of surgery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. We prefer to use a free vascularized fibular graft rather than a proximal femoral osteotomy in these patients because the procedure revascularizes part of the femoral head, preserves the osseous anatomy of the proximal part of the femur, and preserves normal abductor function. Additionally, it is relatively easy to convert this procedure to a total hip arthroplasty when necessary. Our study also supports the proposition that periacetabular osteotomies may provide benefit in the treatment of osteonecrosis of the femoral head in dysplastic hips. This proposition, however, must be evaluated experimentally prior to any consideration for clinical implementation.</p>
<p id="P33">All prognostic factors must be evaluated when a treatment plan is being devised for a patient with osteonecrosis of the femoral head. Previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> have identified a large lesion, a lateral lesion, linear femoral head collapse, arthritic change, and certain etiologies (posttraumatic, idiopathic, and alcohol-related) as poor prognostic factors. These studies also have suggested that there is an interplay between these risk factors and that no one factor is solely predictive of hip survival. Our data suggest that developmental dysplasia of the hip is an additional risk factor for progression of collapse and conversion to a total hip arthroplasty.</p>
<sec id="S11">
<title>Limitations of the Study</title>
<p id="P34">The center-edge angle of Wiberg measured on the anteroposterior pelvic radiograph was the sole radiographic indicator of dysplasia in this retrospective study. This single radiographic view is a relatively insensitive tool for quantification of the degree of dysplasia; inclusion of a false-profile radiograph and/or axial imaging would have been preferable<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Considering the findings of our study, we recommend making a false-profile radiograph in addition to an anteroposterior pelvic radiograph, and we now do so when evaluating patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head and developmental dysplasia of the hip.</p>
<p id="P35">The duration of radiographic follow-up in our study was insufficient to predict long-term results. Furthermore, we can make no determinations about the functional status of these patients. Our clinical follow-up was most frequently performed by the referring orthopaedic surgeons, without use of uniform outcomes instruments. Conversion to a total hip arthroplasty is not a firm clinical end point, as the indications for total hip arthroplasty vary among surgeons. Thus, our clinical follow-up was qualitative at best. Routine postoperative Harris hip scores and other objective measures are currently being recorded for future patient management considerations.</p>
<p id="P36">In summary, a lower center-edge angle and, to a lesser extent, laterality of the osteonecrotic lesion were found to be associated with a significantly higher risk of progression of femoral head collapse and conversion to a total hip arthroplasty following free vascularized fibular grafting. The orientation of the acetabulum and the magnitude of developmental dysplasia of the hip should be included in the preoperative assessment of patients with osteonecrosis of the femoral head.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S12">
<title>Appendix</title>
<p id="P37">A table showing the classification used at our institution (Duke Classification) and the distribution of hips in the present study within that classification is available with the electronic versions of this article, on our web site at <uri>jbjs.org</uri> (go to the article citation and click on “Supplementary Material”) and on our quarterly CD-ROM (call our subscription department, at 781-449-9780, to order the CD-ROM). ▪</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn>
<p><bold>A commentary is available with the electronic versions of this article, on our web site (<uri>www.jbjs.org</uri>) and on our quarterly CD-ROM (call our subscription department, at 781-449-9780, to order the CD-ROM).</bold></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors did not receive grants or outside funding in support of their research for or preparation of this manuscript. They did not receive payments or other benefits or a commitment or agreement to provide such benefits from a commercial entity. No commercial entity paid or directed, or agreed to pay or direct, any benefits to any research fund, foundation, educational institution, or other charitable or nonprofit organization with which the authors are affiliated or associated.</p>
</fn>
<fn>
<p><italic>Investigation performed at the Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina</italic></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">ARCO (Association Research Circulation Osseous)</string-name>. <source>Committee on terminology and classification</source>. ARCO News. <year>1992</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>-6.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Bozic KJ</string-name>, Zurakowski D, Thornhill TS. Survivorship analysis of hips treated with core decompression for nontraumatic osteonecrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>-9.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Lavernia CJ</string-name>, Sierra RJ, Grieco FR. Osteonecrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>-61.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Castro FP</string-name> Jr, Barrack RL. Core decompression and conservative treatment for avascular necrosis of the femoral head: a meta-analysis. <source>Am J Orthop</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>-94.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Fairbank AC</string-name>, Bhatia D, Jinnah RH, Hungerford DS. Long-term results of core decompression for ischaemic necrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>-9.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Mont MA</string-name>, Jones LC, Pacheco I, Hungerford DS. Radiographic predictors of outcome of core decompression for hips with osteonecrosis stage III. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>354</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>-68.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Judet H</string-name>, Gilbert A. Long-term results of free vascularized fibular grafting for femoral head necrosis. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>386</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>-9.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Scully SP</string-name>, Aaron RK, Urbaniak JR. Survival analysis of hips treated with core decompression or vascularized fibular grafting because of avascular necrosis. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1270</fpage>-5.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Urbaniak JR</string-name>, Coogan PG, Gunneson EB, Nunley JA. Treatment of osteonecrosis of the femoral head with free vascularized fibular grafting. A long-term follow-up study of one hundred and three hips. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>681</fpage>-94.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Steinberg ME</string-name>, Bands RE, Parry S, Hoffman E, Chan T, Hartman KM. Does lesion size affect the outcome in avascular necrosis? <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>367</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>-71.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Dean GS</string-name>, Kime RC, Fitch RD, Gunneson E, Urbaniak JR. Treatment of osteonecrosis in the hip of pediatric patients by free vascularized fibular graft. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>386</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>-13.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Ohzono K</string-name>, Saito M, Takaoka K, Ono K, Saito S, Nishina T, Kadowaki T. Natural history of nontraumatic avascular necrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>-72.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Ficat RP</string-name>. Idiopathic bone necrosis of the femoral head. Early diagnosis and treatment. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>-9.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Steinberg ME</string-name>, Hayken GD, Steinberg DR. A quantitative system for staging avascular necrosis. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>-41.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Marcus ND</string-name>, Enneking WF, Massam RA. The silent hip in idiopathic aseptic necrosis. Treatment by bone-grafting. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>1351</fpage>-66.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Berend KR</string-name>, Gunneson EE, Urbaniak JR. Free vascularized fibular grafting for the treatment of postcollapse osteonecrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>-93.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Wiberg G.</string-name> Shelf operation in congenital dysplasia of the acetabulum and in subluxation and dislocation of the hip. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1953</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-80.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Hadley NA</string-name>, Brown TD, Weinstein SL. The effects of contact pressure elevations and aseptic necrosis on the long-term outcome of congenital hip dislocation. <source>J Orthop Res</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>-13.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Olson SA</string-name>, Bay BK, Hamel A. Biomechanics of the hip joint and the effects of fracture of the acetabulum. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>339</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>-104.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Klaue K</string-name>, Durnin CW, Ganz R. The acetabular rim syndrome. A clinical presentation of dysplasia of the hip. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>-9.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Brown TD</string-name>, Shaw DT. In vitro contact stress distributions in the natural human hip. <source>J Biomech</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>-84.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Gregosiewicz A</string-name>, Wosko I. Risk factors of avascular necrosis in the treatment of congenital dislocation of the hip. <source>J Pediatr Orthop</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-9.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Wagner H.</string-name> Osteotomies for congenital hip dislocation. In: <source>The hip</source>. Proceedings of the Fourth Open Scientific Meeting of the Hip Society. St. Louis: CV Mosby; <year>1976</year>. p <fpage>45</fpage>-66.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Sakano S</string-name>, Hasegawa Y, Torii Y, Kawasaki M, Ishiguro N. Curved intertrochanteric varus osteotomy for osteonecrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>-65.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Beris AE</string-name>, Payatakes AH, Kostopoulos VK, Korompilias AV, Mavrodontidis AN, Vekris MD, Kontogeorgakos VA, Soucacos PN. Non-union of femoral neck fractures with osteonecrosis of the femoral head: treatment with combined free vascularized fibular grafting and subtrochanteric valgus osteotomy. <source>Orthop Clin North Am</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>-43, ix.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Ito H</string-name>, Matsuno T, Omizu N, Aoki Y, Minami A. Mid-term prognosis of nontraumatic osteonecrosis of the femoral head. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>-801.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Dean MT</string-name>, Cabanela ME. Transtrochanteric anterior rotational osteotomy for avascular necrosis of the femoral head. Long-term results. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>-601.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Shannon BD</string-name>, Trousdale RT. Femoral osteotomies for avascular necrosis of the femoral head. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>418</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>-40.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Matsuo K</string-name>, Hirohata T, Sugioka Y, Ikeda M, Fukuda A. Influence of alcohol intake, cigarette smoking, and occupational status on idiopathic osteonecrosis of the femoral head. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>234</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>-23.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western">Lequesne M</string-name>, de Sèze S. Le faux profil du bassin. Nouvelle incidence radiographique pour l'étude de la hanche. Son utilité dans les dysplasies et les différentes coxopathies. <source>Rev Rhum</source>. <year>1961</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>643</fpage>-52.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>