<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:r="http://www.rsuitecms.com/rsuite/ns/metadata" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" r:rsuiteId="2141279" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jbjsam</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Bone Joint Surg Am</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbjsam</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9355</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1535-1386</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta r:rsuiteId="2141280"><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JBJS-D-18-00970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.18.00970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00006</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>0170</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Scientific Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Military Extremity Trauma Amputation/Limb Salvage (METALS) Study</article-title><subtitle>Outcomes of Amputation Compared with Limb Salvage Following Major Upper-Extremity Trauma</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9066-1088</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>Stuart L.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0061-155X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayda</surname><given-names>Roman</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8662-5295</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Andrew T.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1419-4515</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlini</surname><given-names>Anthony R.</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0275-4223</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ficke</surname><given-names>James R.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5480-8502</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>Ellen J.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><on-behalf-of>on behalf of the METALS Study Group</on-behalf-of><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Health Policy and Management, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, Maryland</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Brown University Warren Alpert School of Medicine, Providence, Rhode Island</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, University of North Carolina School of Medicine, Chapel Hill, North Carolina</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">E-mail address for R. Hayda: <email>roman_hayda@brown.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Investigation performed at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, Maryland</italic></p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>*</label><p>The members of the Military Extremity Trauma Amputation/Limb Salvage (METALS) Study Group included Roman Hayda, MD, William C. Doukas, MD, H. Michael Frisch, MD, Romney C. Andersen, MD, John J. Keeling, MD, Michael T. Mazurek, MD (deceased), Paul F. Pasquina, MD, Harold J. Wain, PhD, Anthony R. Carlini, MS, James R. Ficke, MD, and Ellen J. MacKenzie, PhD.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3"><p><bold>Disclosure:</bold> This study was funded in part by a grant from the U.S. Department of Defense, Military Amputee Research Program of the United States Army Medical Research Acquisition Activity (USAMRAA) (Contract Number: W81XWH-06-1-0361), and by a grant from the National Institutes of Health (T32 AR067708). On the <bold>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest</bold> forms, <italic toggle="yes">which are provided with the online version of the article</italic>, one or more of the authors checked “yes” to indicate that the author had a relevant financial relationship in the biomedical arena outside the submitted work and “yes” to indicate that the author had other relationships or activities that could be perceived to influence, or have the potential to influence, what was written in this work (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JBJS/F370">http://links.lww.com/JBJS/F370</ext-link>).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>101</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1470</fpage><lpage>1478</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2019 by The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Incorporated</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="JBJS.18.00970.pdf" xlink:title="pdf"/><self-uri content-type="disclosure-pdf" xlink:href="JBJS.18.00970.disclosure.pdf"/><self-uri xlink:href="JBJS.18.00970.ds01.pdf" xlink:title="data-supplement-pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Severe upper-extremity injuries account for almost one-half of all extremity trauma in recent conflicts in the Global War on Terror. Few long-term outcomes studies address severe combat-related upper-extremity injuries. This study’s objective was to describe long-term functional outcomes of amputation compared with those of limb salvage in Global War on Terror veterans who sustained severe upper-extremity injuries. Limb salvage was hypothesized to result in better arm and hand function scores, overall functional status, and quality of life, with similar pain interference.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>This retrospective cohort study utilized data from the Military Extremity Trauma Amputation/Limb Salvage (METALS) study for a subset of 155 individuals who sustained major upper-extremity injuries treated with amputation or limb salvage. Participants were interviewed by telephone 40 months after injury, assessing social support, personal habits, and patient-reported outcome instruments for function, activity, depression, pain, and posttraumatic stress. Outcomes were evaluated for participants with severe upper-extremity injuries and were compared with participants with concomitant severe, lower-extremity injury. The analysis of outcomes comparing limb salvage with amputation was restricted to the 137 participants with a unilateral upper-extremity injury because of the small number of patients with bilateral upper-extremity injuries (n = 18).</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Overall, participants with upper-extremity injuries reported moderate to high levels of physical and psychosocial disability. Short Musculoskeletal Function Assessment (SMFA) scores were high across domains; 19.4% screened positive for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and 12.3% were positive for depression. Nonetheless, 63.6% of participants were working, were on active duty, or were attending school, and 38.7% of participants were involved in vigorous recreational activities. No significant differences in outcomes were observed between patients who underwent limb salvage and those who underwent amputation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Severe, combat-related upper-extremity injuries result in diminished self-reported function and psychosocial health. Our results suggest that long-term outcomes are equivalent for those treated with amputation or limb salvage. Addressing or preventing PTSD, depression, chronic pain, and associated health habits may result in less disability burden in this population.</p></sec><sec><title>Level of Evidence:</title><p>Therapeutic <underline>Level III</underline>. See Instructions for Authors for a complete description of levels of evidence.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Upper-extremity injuries are common among combat casualties, most often resulting from high-energy explosives such as improvised explosive devices. Extremity injuries accounted for 39% to 54%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1 bib2">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> of all combat wounds sustained by injured U.S. service members in the Global War on Terror<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup>, among which 41% to 52% of wounds were to the upper extremities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup>. Between 2001 and 2011, there were 2,037 traumatic major amputations (i.e., at, or proximal to, the radiocarpal or tibiotalar joint) sustained by service members during these conflicts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup>, with 14% to 25% involving the upper extremities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8 bib9 bib10 bib11">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup>. The remaining severe upper-extremity injuries were surgically reconstructed.</p><p>The upper extremity is generally thought to be less prone to complications with reconstruction, and when amputation is performed, prosthetics often cannot fully replicate upper-extremity function despite continuing advances in technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12 bib13 bib14">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup>. Consequently, reconstruction is attempted in most mangled upper-extremity trauma injuries, although amputation may be selectively indicated. In other limited circumstances, typically those limited to civilian-type injuries, replantation may be feasible<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14 bib15 bib16">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p>There have been few studies showing long-term outcomes of combat-related, major trauma to the upper extremity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18 bib19">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref></sup>. Without outcomes data, health services lack information to perform evidence-based decision-making and counseling while resource allocation is made difficult. A few studies of severe upper-extremity injury outcomes have been performed in civilian populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21 bib22 bib23">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup>. However, with differences in military and civilian injuries and the advances in prosthetic technology and surgical care available to service members, the civilian results may not be generalizable to military populations.</p><p>The objective of this study was to describe long-term functional outcomes among service members who sustained major upper-extremity injuries in combat during the Global War on Terror by comparing differences between patients who underwent limb salvage and those who underwent amputation. We hypothesized that limb salvage would result in better arm and hand function scores, overall functional status, and quality of life and that pain interference would be similar because of chronic pain in patients who underwent limb salvage and prosthesis-related discomfort or phantom limb pain in patients who underwent amputation.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This retrospective cohort study utilized data from a subset of individuals from the Military Extremity Trauma Amputation/Limb Salvage (METALS) study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup>. In their study, Doukas et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> analyzed outcomes following lower-extremity trauma; the current study focuses on patients who sustained major upper-extremity trauma.</p><sec><title>Study Population</title><p>Active-duty personnel and reservists who sustained major limb trauma while deployed in Iraq or Afghanistan between 2003 and 2007 were eligible for participation in the METALS study. Major limb trauma was defined as an injury at, or proximal to, either the hindfoot or radiocarpal joint that resulted in an amputation or required reconstruction that included revascularization, bone-grafting or transport, local or free-flap coverage, repair or treatment of a major nerve deficit, or treatment for compartment syndrome. Patients with persistent brain injury (Glasgow Coma Scale score of &lt;15 points at discharge) or spinal cord injury resulting in paraplegia or quadriplegia were excluded.</p><p>The overall METALS study included 429 participants with complete medical records who consented to the study. Of the initial 868 initial patients screened, 519 (59.8%) were located and agreed to be interviewed, 202 (23.3%) declined to participate, and 147 (16.9%) did not respond. Of those who agreed to participate, 69 were ineligible and 21 had incomplete records. More detailed patient selection has been described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup>. This study focuses on 155 individuals who sustained METALS-eligible upper-extremity injuries.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterizing Patients and Injuries</title><p>Information obtained from the interviews was used to characterize participant demographic characteristics, social support (Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup>), branch of military service and grade (highest while on active duty), combat experiences (Combat Experiences Questionnaire<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup>), and health habits (tobacco and alcohol use<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup>).</p><p>Injuries were classified using medical record documentation of a stateside military treatment facility. Amputations were categorized by anatomic level. Fractures of salvaged limbs were classified by bone segment. Additional injuries were also documented, including segmental bone loss, skin defect, burns, extent of muscle and/or tendon injury, and location and severity of all neurovascular injuries.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of Outcomes</title><p>Participants were interviewed by telephone and completed self-reported outcome measures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> including the Short Musculoskeletal Function Assessment (SMFA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup>, Paffenbarger Physical Activity Questionnaire<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30 bib31">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref></sup>, Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale Revised (CESDR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup>, PTSD (Posttraumatic Stress Disorder) checklist (PCL)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref></sup>, and Chronic Pain Grade (CPG)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="app1">Appendix 1</xref> for outcomes measurement tools). Major role activity participation was assessed by standard questions pertaining to involvement in usual activities in the past week.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Outcomes were evaluated first for all patients with any upper-extremity injury and then separately for those with or without a concomitant METALS-eligible lower-extremity injury. Analysis comparing limb salvage with amputation was restricted to the subjects with a unilateral upper-extremity injury because of the small number with bilateral upper-extremity injuries.</p><p>Multiple regression techniques were used to examine differences in outcomes associated with limb salvage compared with amputation while adjusting for patient characteristics and their injuries, together with the time since the injury. Continuous outcomes were modeled using linear regressions, and the probability of dichotomous outcomes was modeled using logistic regressions. Significance was set at α = 0.05. Statistical analyses were performed using SAS, version 9.1 (SAS Institute).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Characteristics of the Participants</title><p>Participants with major trauma to ≥1 upper extremity had a mean age of 30 years (range, 22 to 55 years), and the majority were male (98.1%), non-Hispanic white (81.1%), married (50.3%), and senior enlisted (53.5%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). At the time of the injury, participants were most commonly active-duty Army (68%), Marines (20%), or reservists (8%). There were no significant differences between the limb salvage group and the amputation group with regard to the distribution of participants’ age, sex, race or ethnicity, education, social support, combat experiences, or highest military rank. Participants were interviewed at a mean of 40 months (range, 12 to 70 months) after the injury.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE I</label><caption><p>Characteristics of METALS Study Participants with Major Upper-Extremity Injuries by Presence of Bilateral Injury and by Amputation Compared with Limb Salvage for Those with Unilateral Injuries</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2">All Participants (N = 155)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2">Bilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">*</xref> (N = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salvage (N = 104)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amputation (N = 33)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 18 to 24 years</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 25 to 29 years</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥30 years</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.9%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male sex<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race or ethnicity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Non-Hispanic white</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.7%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Non-Hispanic black</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">High school graduate or less<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marital status at time of injury<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Married</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Never married</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Living with a partner</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Separated, divorced, widow</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Social support<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low (0 to 70)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.9%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Moderate (71 to 80)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High (81 to 100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Military rank<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Junior enlisted (E1 to E4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Senior enlisted (E5 to E9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.6%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Officers</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of combat experiences<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0 to 5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 6 to 8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 9 to 11</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 12 to 17</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.1%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>*</label><p>Bilateral upper-extremity injuries included 11 cases of bilateral limb salvage, 4 cases of bilateral amputation, and 3 cases of combined amputation and limb salvage (i.e., 1 of each type of treatment).</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>†</label><p>The values are given as the percentage of patients.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Characteristics of the Injuries</title><p>Overall, 137 participants sustained METALS-eligible injuries to 1 upper extremity (104 salvages; 33 amputations) and 18 participants sustained METALS-eligible injuries to both upper extremities (11 bilateral salvage, 4 bilateral amputation, and 3 salvage and amputation), for a total of 173 limb injuries. All amputations took place within 9 days of the initial injury (mean [and standard deviation], 1 ± 2 days [range, 0 to 9 days]). The majority of amputations were at the transradial level (19 [43.2%] of 44) or the transhumeral level (14 [31.8%] of 44) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). Among the 129 salvaged limbs, 70.5% (91 limbs) had ≥1 fracture of the radius and/or ulna and 33.3% (43 limbs) had ≥1 humeral fracture. The 3 most common METALS-eligible injuries and/or procedures in salvaged limbs were bone-grafting or transport for a segmental defect (41.9%), complete deficit of a major nerve (36.4%), and local or free-flap coverage (33.3%). Fifty participants (32.3%) had 56 associated METALS-eligible lower-extremity injuries.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE II</label><caption><p>METALS Eligibility: Characteristics of Injured Limbs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All METALS Upper-Extremity Injuries (N = 173)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">With METALS Lower-Extremity Injury (N = 56)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Without METALS Lower-Extremity Injury (N = 117)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amputated limb level<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Shoulder disarticulation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (15.9%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (19.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Transhumeral<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (31.8%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (37.5%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (30.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Transradial<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (43.2%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (62.5%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (38.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Wrist disarticulation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (9.1%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (11.1%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salvaged limb injuries and/or procedures<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn5">‡</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Bone graft or bone transport for segmental bone defect<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (41.9%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (39.6%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (43.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Complete deficit of major nerve<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (36.4%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (31.3%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (39.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Local or free flap coverage<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (33.3%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (29.2%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (35.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Compartment syndrome or muscle loss requiring fasciotomy<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (23.3%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (31.3%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (18.5%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Revascularization<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (8.5%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (6.3%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (9.9%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><label>*</label><p>The values are given as the number of patients.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>†</label><p>The values are given as the number of patients, with the percentage in parentheses.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><label>‡</label><p>The numbers will not add to the number of patients because some patients met multiple criteria.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Outcomes at Follow-up</title><p>Overall, participants with any METALS-eligible upper-extremity injury reported moderate to high levels of physical and psychosocial disability (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table III</xref>). In all domains of the SMFA except mobility, subjects scored significantly higher (worse function) than population norms (norms: 12.7 for total dysfunction, 13.6 for mobility, 11.8 for daily activities, 20.5 for emotional status, and 6.0 for arm and hand function)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup>. Notably, more dysfunction was reported for arm and hand function (21.8) and emotional status (44.1). Nonetheless, 38.7% reported engaging in vigorous sports or recreational activities, and 63.6% were working, were on active duty, or were attending school. Eighteen percent reported having pain that interfered with their normal activities, compared with 16% in the general population. Only 9.1% reported being pain-free (42% in the general population)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup>. Depressive symptoms were reported by 40.0% of participants, with 12.3% screening positive for possible or probable depression and 19.4% screening positive for PTSD. Additionally, 28.9% reported current tobacco smoking and 25.8% had self-reported drinking that indicated a possible (CAGE score = 1; 11.6%) or probable (CAGE score ≥ 2; 14.2%) drinking problem<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table IV</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE III</label><caption><p>Unadjusted Outcomes of METALS Participants with Any Upper-Extremity Injury at the Time of Interview</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2">All Participants</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2">Bilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salvage</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amputation</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of participants</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean SMFA scores<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn6">*</xref> <italic toggle="yes">(points)</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Total dysfunction</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Daily activities</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Emotional status</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Arm and hand function</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Mobility<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn7">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Engaged in vigorous sports or recreational activities</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">With depressive symptoms</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">With possible or probable depression</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screened positive for PTSD</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Working or on active duty at time of interview</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.9%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Working, on active duty, or in school at time of interview</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.6%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean pain intensity within 4 weeks prior to interview</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">With pain interfering with activity</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn6"><label>*</label><p>Higher SMFA scores represent worse function in a given domain.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn7"><label>†</label><p>The comparison of the unilateral salvage group and amputation group was significant at p &lt; 0.05. The mean difference was 7.8 (95% confidence interval, 0.06 to 15.4).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE IV</label><caption><p>Tobacco Smoking and Alcohol Drinking Status at the Time of Interview in Participants with Any Upper-Extremity Injury</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2">All Participants (N = 155)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2">Bilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries (N = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salvage (N = 104)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amputation (N = 33)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current smoking status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No smoking in past 4 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Current tobacco smoking</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  &lt;20 cigarettes per day</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.9%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  ≥20 cigarettes per day</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.8%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current drinking status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No drinks in past 4 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Current alcohol intake</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  ≤3 drinks per week</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  4 to 13 drinks per week</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.1%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  ≥14 drinks per week</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.0%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAGE score</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0 (no drinking problem)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.9%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1 (possible drinking problem)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.6%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥2 (probable drinking problem)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.4%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Comparison of Outcome by Treatment</title><p>Outcomes by the presence of a unilateral injury compared with a bilateral injury and by amputation compared with limb salvage are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table III</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">Tables V</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl6">VI</xref> summarize the results of the regressions. Covariates included in the final regression models were the presence of a major lower-extremity injury, age, time to interview, military rank, combat experiences, and perceived social support. Race or ethnicity was removed because it was not a significant predictor in any regression. Education was also removed because it correlated with military rank and could not be considered a predictor of outcome as it was assessed at the time of the interview.</p><table-wrap id="tbl5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE V</label><caption><p>Regression Results: Effect of Upper-Extremity Amputation Status on SMFA Scores of Participants with Unilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries (N = 137)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Dysfunction<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn8">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mobility Subscore<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn8">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Daily Activities Subscore<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn8">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Emotional Subscore<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn8">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arm and Hand Subscore<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn8">*</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper-extremity amputation</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.95 (−8.78 to 2.87)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.47 (−12.1 to 1.13)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.53 (−9.23 to 6.16)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.68 (−16.1 to 0.78)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.23 (−5.32 to 9.79)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">METALS lower-extremity injury</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (1.70 to 12.37)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (13.5 to 25.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.61 (−2.43 to 11.65)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.25 (−2.49 to 12.99)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.46 (−9.37 to 4.45)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (0.34 to 1.12)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (0.16 to 1.05)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (0.05 to 1.09)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (0.27 to 1.41)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (0.46 to 1.48)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Months to interview</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (−0.42 to −0.05)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.20 (−0.41 to 0.01)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (−0.64 to −0.15)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.19 (−0.46 to 0.08)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.11 (−0.35 to 0.13)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rank</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Junior enlisted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Senior enlisted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.14 (−10.9 to 0.64)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.47 (−8.00 to 5.07)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.62 (−13.2 to 2.00)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−8.00 (−16.4 to 0.38)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.16 (−13.6 to 1.33)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Commissioned officer</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.79 (−17.0 to 1.44)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.71 (−17.2 to 3.73)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.55 (−17.7 to 6.63)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−15.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (−28.8 to −2.01)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.14 (−17.1 to 6.82)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of combat experiences</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (0.38 to 1.70)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (0.14 to 1.63)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72 (−0.15 to 1.59)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (1.11 to 3.02)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72 (−0.13 to 1.58)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Social support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low (≤70)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Moderate (71 to 80)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (−13.4 to −1.49)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.34 (−12.1 to 1.41)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.22 (−14.1 to 1.66)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−14.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (−23.2 to −5.87)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.20 (−12.9 to 2.54)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High (&gt;80)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (−14.4 to −1.44)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.28 (−12.6 to 2.07)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−9.65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">†</xref> (−18.2 to −1.07)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−15.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">‡</xref> (−25.2 to −6.33)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.94 (−10.4 to 6.49)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn8"><label>*</label><p>The values are given as the regression coefficient, with the 95% confidence interval in parentheses; higher SMFA scores represent worse function in a given domain.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn9"><label>†</label><p>Significant at p &lt; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn10"><label>‡</label><p>Significant at p &lt; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE VI</label><caption><p>Regression Results: Adjusted Odds of Depression, PTSD, Role Participation, Engagement in Vigorous Sports, and Pain Interference for Participants with Unilateral Upper-Extremity Injuries (N = 137)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screens Positive for Depression<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screens Positive for PTSD<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Currently Working, Active Duty, or in School<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Engaged in Vigorous Sports<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">*</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pain Interferes with Activity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">*</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper-extremity amputation</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28 (0.04 to 1.76)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32 (0.40 to 4.38)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29 (0.50 to 3.31)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.37 to 2.16)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05 (0.35 to 3.16)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">METALS lower-extremity injury</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.77 (0.51 to 6.06)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71 (0.23 to 2.25)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (0.54 to 2.96)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57 (0.71 to 3.46)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.27 to 2.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (0.99 to 1.17)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn12">†</xref> (1.01 to 1.20)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.90 to 1.01)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (0.96 to 1.08)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06 (0.99 to 1.14)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Months to interview</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.94 to 1.03)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.98 to 1.06)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">‡</xref> (1.03 to 1.10)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.99 to 1.04)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.96 to 1.03)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rank</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Junior enlisted</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Non-commissioned officer</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43 (0.10 to 1.77)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35 (0.11 to 1.19)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17 (0.47 to 2.91)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72 (0.72 to 4.08)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33 (0.42 to 4.18)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Commissioned officer</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22 (0.02 to 3.07)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn12">†</xref> (0.00 to 0.56)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.91 (0.76 to 20.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn12">†</xref> (1.38 to 23.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64 (0.09 to 4.33)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of combat experiences</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn12">†</xref> (1.03 to 1.52)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">‡</xref> (1.09 to 1.59)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.84 to 1.05)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.89 to 1.09)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 (0.99 to 1.31)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Social support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low (≤70)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Moderate (71 to 80)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">‡</xref> (0.02 to 0.48)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">‡</xref> (0.08 to 0.71)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 (0.39 to 2.45)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20 (0.49 to 2.93)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46 (0.16 to 1.36)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> High (&gt;80)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23 (0.05 to 1.07)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">‡</xref> (0.01 to 0.44)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07 (0.71 to 6.03)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32 (0.50 to 3.46)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48 (0.14 to 1.66)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn11"><label>*</label><p>The values are given as the odds ratio, with the 95% confidence interval in parentheses.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn12"><label>†</label><p>Significantly different at p &lt; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn13"><label>‡</label><p>Significantly different at p &lt; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After adjusting for covariates, there were no significant differences in outcomes between participants who underwent unilateral limb salvage and participants who underwent unilateral amputation, including any SMFA domain scores or rates of depression; PTSD; return to work, active duty, or school; participation in vigorous activity; or pain interference. However, several other factors were associated with the outcomes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">Tables V</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl6">VI</xref>). The presence of a lower-extremity injury was associated with worse SMFA total dysfunction scores (p &lt; 0.05) and mobility scores (p &lt; 0.01). Older age was associated with worse SMFA scores in all domains (p &lt; 0.05) and with 10% higher odds of PTSD (p &lt; 0.05). Commissioned officers had better SMFA emotional scores (p &lt; 0.05), were 97% less likely to screen positive for PTSD (p &lt; 0.05), and were 5.7 times more likely to engage in vigorous activities (p &lt; 0.05). More combat experience was correlated with worse SMFA total dysfunction scores (p &lt; 0.01), mobility scores (p &lt; 0.05), and emotional scores (p &lt; 0.01) and increased the likelihood of depression by 25% (p &lt; 0.05) and the likelihood of PTSD by 32% (p &lt; 0.01). More social support was associated with a lower likelihood of PTSD (p &lt; 0.01) and improved SMFA emotional and activity scores (p &lt; 0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study presents the first comparison of long-term outcomes following major upper-extremity trauma sustained by U.S. military personnel in the Global War on Terror treated with limb salvage or amputation. Like patients with lower-extremity injuries in the METALS study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup>, moderate to high levels of physical and psychosocial disability were reported by participants with upper-extremity injuries compared with general population norms. Although unique functional limitations specific to the site of injury exist, similar, significant rates of overall disability persisted in this population regardless of whether the upper or lower extremity was involved and irrespective of treatment by amputation or salvage.</p><p>Although basic surgical principles may be similar when managing severe upper-extremity or lower-extremity injury, functional and anatomic differences must be considered when deciding whether to perform limb salvage or amputation. Motion, dexterity, and sensibility, which are believed to be critical in the upper extremity, cannot be fully replicated by a prosthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup>. Tintle et al. suggested that a “bad hand” may be more functional than a “good amputation” in the upper extremity, but this difference may not be as important in the lower extremity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup>. The limitations of prosthetic technology may make limb salvage more attractive than amputation in the upper extremity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup>. However, despite the hypothesis favoring limb salvage over amputation, our results did not demonstrate any significant differences in outcomes for those undergoing limb salvage compared with amputation following a unilateral, major upper-extremity injury.</p><p>To our knowledge, there have been no prior studies directly comparing long-term outcomes of reconstruction with amputation after upper-extremity injuries in military or civilian populations; however, there have been a few studies in civilian populations comparing replantation with amputation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup>. The destructive mechanisms of war injury usually preclude replantation, and resources required for a replantation surgical procedure are usually lacking in the battle zone. Nonetheless, revascularization, nerve and tendon repair, and complex osteosynthesis were components of reconstruction in our cohort, making civilian replantation reports the closest counterpart for comparison. In a cohort of 44 patients with major traumatic amputations (50% replantation cases) at a mean follow-up of 7.3 years, patients who underwent a replantation had better function than those treated with amputation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup>. Similarly, patient-reported function was compared following major traumatic amputations treated with either replantation (n = 9) or amputation (n = 22) at a mean follow-up of 10.0 years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup>, finding that successful replantation was more favorable than amputation. A systematic review of transradial, elbow disarticulation, or transhumeral traumatic amputations compared functional and psychological outcomes among 301 patients who underwent replantation and 172 patients who underwent revision amputation from 41 observational studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup>. The authors concluded that replantation had good functional results and higher satisfaction, independent of objective functional outcome. These civilian studies suggest that upper-extremity replantation leads to improved outcomes over amputation with prosthetic fitting, in contrast to the results of our study. These differences suggest that data from civilian trauma populations may not be directly applicable to military populations given the unique mechanisms of injury and likely differences in immediate care, social support, and access to rehabilitation and prosthetic devices.</p><p>The comparable outcomes that we found may be explained by several factors related to improved amputee care. Military amputees have access to the best prosthetic technology available with few financial restrictions. Modern prosthetic devices capable of complex tasks and with many degrees of freedom such as myoelectric limbs were also routinely available to this cohort<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>. Reiber et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup> showed that military personnel who have undergone upper-extremity amputation take advantage of the newest prosthetic technologies, with each patient receiving nearly 5 different prosthetic devices, on average, since amputation. However, Gajewski and Granville<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup> suggested that focused rehabilitation for up to a year or even longer and the dedication of physiatrists, therapists, and patients improve functional outcomes in military amputees. Lastly, robust social support services for amputees likely also play an important role.</p><p>The rates of depression and PTSD among injured veterans in this study were concerning. In prior studies of Global War on Terror veterans, the rates of depression and PTSD varied substantially depending on definitions, method of diagnosis (e.g., self-report or formal evaluation), and population studied (military operation and armed service branch). Using the same criteria as the current study, the prevalence of major depression has been reported to be 9.3% to 9.6% and the prevalence of PTSD has been reported to be 12.0% to 23.9% among injured soldiers, which is similar to the 12.3% of soldiers with possible or probable depression and 19.4% of soldiers who screened positive for PTSD found in this study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup>. Alcohol use and misuse by this cohort were higher than national figures: 81.3% of participants were current drinkers compared with 68.8% for adults who were 18 to 44 years of age<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref></sup>. Additionally, 25.8% screened positive for a possible alcohol-related problem (CAGE score ≥ 1), compared with 19.4% of participants in the Millennium Cohort Study with combat exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup>. Surprisingly, the mean pain intensity score reported was lowest for patients with bilateral upper-extremity injuries, and only 16.7% reported pain interfering with their normal activities, compared with 16% in the general population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup>. Our findings indicate that, although these service members have access to extensive physical and occupational therapy and mental health support, additional work is needed to optimize outcomes in upper-extremity reconstruction and amputation.</p><p>The limitations of the present investigation included those inherent to any retrospective, observational study, including limitations related to the time since the injury, the use of self-reported measures, and the potential for selection bias as described in the previous METALS study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup>. The modest overall METALS participation rate of 59.8% and the differential rate between the participants who underwent amputation (64%) and those who underwent limb salvage (55%) were a potential source of bias. Although attempts were made at controlling differences between the treatment groups, there may be unmeasured differences between the 2 groups that could result in confounding. However, further analysis of the METALS study cohort has found that there are no major differences between the patients who participated in the study and those who did not consent or could not be located, reducing concerns about potential differences between the participants in each group and generalizability of results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref></sup>.</p><p>Surgical techniques for limb salvage and amputation continue to evolve, as has prosthetic technology since the subjects’ injuries were treated. More refined use of nerve conduits, allograft<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup>, targeted reinnervation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup>, and others may reduce the sequela of severe nerve injury and may provide improved prosthetic function. Enhanced myoelectric prostheses have the potential for greater dexterity and functionality, particularly if coupled with targeted reinnervation. Osseointegrated prostheses, although not approved in the United States, have the potential of obviating socket fit issues, enhancing function of upper-extremity amputees<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref></sup>. These technological and surgical advances in the treatment of severe upper-extremity injury are important and may influence outcomes in an incremental fashion. They should be studied and improved further, but such advances have not fully restored normal function after these complex, multidimensional injuries.</p><p>Severe, combat-related upper-extremity injuries are debilitating in terms of self-reported function and psychosocial health. Our results suggest that there is no difference in outcomes between those treated by amputation or limb salvage. The results of this study do not prescribe treatment by salvage or amputation, but rather point to significant long-term challenges incurred by all severely injured patients. Surgeons must consider each injury in the context of patient needs and the resources available. Developing means of addressing or preventing PTSD, depression, chronic pain, and associated health habits may result in less disability in war casualties with severe upper-extremity injuries.</p></sec><sec id="app1"><title>Appendix</title><p>Supporting material provided by the authors is posted with the online version of this article as a data supplement at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jbjs.org">jbjs.org</ext-link> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JBJS/F371">http://links.lww.com/JBJS/F371</ext-link>).</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>N<sc>ote:</sc> The authors thank the service members and veterans who generously gave their time to participate in the METALS study. They also thank them and all our troops for the sacrifice they make for our country. In addition, the authors thank all of the medics, corpsmen, doctors, nurses, and therapists who cared for the participants in the METALS study. The authors specifically thank those who directly contributed to this research effort, including Major Adam Groth, Commander Robert Beer, Major Travis Burns, Major Anton Lacap, Colonel Charles Scoville (retired), Dr. Timothy McHenry, and Captain Dana C. Covey. The authors also thank the data abstractors (Caren C. Swift, Selina P. Doncevic, Davina Murphy Jeter, Caroline A. Eiteljorge, Patricia Horgas, and Sheila Menagh); Vivian Luu, who assisted in developing the METALS database; and Patti Ephraim, who provided important direction and coordination for the study early in its development. Finally, the authors especially thank their late colleague and METALS coinvestigator and study group author, Commander Michael Mazurek, who died before the current study was completed.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belmont</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCriskin</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burks</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The nature and incidence of musculoskeletal combat wounds in Iraq and Afghanistan (2005-2009)</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>May</month>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e107</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname> <given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belmont</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The nature and extent of war injuries sustained by combat specialty personnel killed and wounded in Afghanistan and Iraq, 2003-2011</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoencamp</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vermetten</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Putter</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leenen</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hamming</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review of the prevalence and characteristics of battle casualties from NATO coalition forces in Iraq and Afghanistan</article-title>. <source>Injury.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Jul</month>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1028</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>Epub 2014 Feb 15</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>U.S. Department of Defense</collab>. <article-title>Defense Casualty Analysis System. Conflict casualties</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dcas.dmdc.osd.mil/dcas/pages/casualties.xhtml">https://dcas.dmdc.osd.mil/dcas/pages/casualties.xhtml</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed 2019 Apr 17</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kragh</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Macaitis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Svoboda</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wenke</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of extremity wounds in Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring Freedom</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma.</source> <year>2007</year> <month>Apr</month>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>254</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfeld</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belmont</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pelvic, spinal and extremity wounds among combat-specific personnel serving in Iraq and Afghanistan (2003-2011): a new paradigm in military musculoskeletal medicine</article-title>. <source>Injury.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1866</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>. <comment>Epub 2013 Aug 11</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Armed Forces Health Surveillance Center (AFHSC)</collab>. <article-title>Amputations of upper and lower extremities, active and reserve components, U.S. Armed Forces, 2000-2011</article-title>. <source>MSMR.</source> <year>2012</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tennent</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wenke</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterisation and outcomes of upper extremity amputations</article-title>. <source>Injury.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>965</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>Epub 2014 Feb 15</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wenke</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ficke</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ten years at war: comprehensive analysis of amputation trends</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg.</source> <year>2012</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>6</issue>)(<supplement>Suppl 5</supplement>):<fpage>S438</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belisle</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wenke</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Return-to-duty rates among US military combat-related amputees in the global war on terror: job description matters</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stinner</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ficke</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Return to duty rate of amputee soldiers in the current conflicts in Afghanistan and Iraq</article-title>. <source>J Trauma.</source> <year>2010</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1476</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stansbury</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lalliss</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Branstetter</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bagg</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Holcomb</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Amputations in U.S. military personnel in the current conflicts in Afghanistan and Iraq</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma.</source> <year>2008</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tintle</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baechler</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nanos</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forsberg</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reoperations following combat-related upper-extremity amputations</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2012</year> <month>Aug</month> <day>15</day>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>e1191</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tintle</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baechler</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nanos</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names> <suffix>3rd</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forsberg</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Traumatic and trauma-related amputations: part II: upper extremity and future directions</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2010</year> <month>Dec</month> <day>15</day>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>2934</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pet</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lussiez</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Means</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cederna</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of patient-reported outcomes after traumatic upper extremity amputation: replantation versus prosthetic rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>Injury.</source> <year>2016</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2783</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>Epub 2016 Oct 19</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cederna</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Urbanchek</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Langhals</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical factors associated with replantation after traumatic major upper extremity amputation</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Oct</month>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>911</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Firrell</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Breidenbach</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Major replantation versus revision amputation and prosthetic fitting in the upper extremity: a late functional outcomes study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am.</source> <year>1998</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>783</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodruff</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Galarneau</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sack</surname> <given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCabe</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dye</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Combat amputees’ health-related quality of life and psychological outcomes: a brief report from the Wounded Warrior Recovery Project</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg.</source> <year>2017</year> <month>Mar</month>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>592</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wenke</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Common factors and outcome in late upper extremity amputations after military injury</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Apr</month>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glebus</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Disability following combat-sustained nerve injury of the upper limb</article-title>. <source>Bone Joint J.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>96-B</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>254</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paryavi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pensy</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chia</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eglseder</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Salvage of upper extremities with humeral fracture and associated brachial artery injury</article-title>. <source>Injury.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1870</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mattiassich</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rittenschober</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dorninger</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rois</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mittermayr</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ortmaier</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ponschab</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Katzensteiner</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larcher</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term outcome following upper extremity replantation after major traumatic amputation</article-title>. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord.</source> <year>2017</year> <month>Feb</month> <day>10</day>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schuurman</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Minnen</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Replantation versus prosthetic fitting in traumatic arm amputations: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source> <year>2015</year> <month>Sep</month> <day>4</day>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e0137729</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Märdian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krapohl</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roffeis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Disch</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schaser</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schwabe</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Complete major amputation of the upper extremity: early results and initial treatment algorithm</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg.</source> <year>2015</year> <month>Mar</month>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>586</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doukas</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hayda</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frisch</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mazurek</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ficke</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keeling</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pasquina</surname> <given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wain</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlini</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Military Extremity Trauma Amputation/Limb Salvage (METALS) study: outcomes of amputation versus limb salvage following major lower-extremity trauma</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Jan</month> <day>16</day>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zimet</surname> <given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farley</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Werkman</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berkoff</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric characteristics of the Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support</article-title>. <source>J Pers Assess.</source> <year>1990</year> <season>Winter</season>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>3-4</issue>):<fpage>610</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoge</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Messer</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGurk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cotting</surname> <given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koffman</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Combat duty in Iraq and Afghanistan, mental health problems, and barriers to care</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> <year>2004</year> <month>Jul</month> <day>1</day>;<volume>351</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ewing</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Detecting alcoholism. The CAGE questionnaire</article-title>. <source>JAMA.</source> <year>1984</year> <month>Oct</month> <day>12</day>;<volume>252</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1905</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Swiontkowski</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Engelberg</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Short Musculoskeletal Function Assessment questionnaire: validity, reliability, and responsiveness</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>1999</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1245</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paffenbarger</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wing</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity as an index of heart attack risk in college alumni</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol.</source> <year>1978</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pate</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pratt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haskell</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Macera</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buchner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ettinger</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kriska</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paffenbarger</surname> <suffix>Jr</suffix> <given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pollock</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rippe</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sallis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilmore</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and public health. A recommendation from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the American College of Sports Medicine</article-title>. <source>JAMA.</source> <year>1995</year> <month>Feb</month> <day>1</day>;<volume>273</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haskell</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whitt</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Strath</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bassett</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Emplaincourt</surname> <given-names>PO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Compendium of physical activities: an update of activity codes and MET intensities</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc.</source> <year>2000</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>)(<supplement>Suppl</supplement>):<fpage>S498</fpage>-<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ybarra</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muntaner</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tien</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale: Review and Revision (CESD and CESD-R)</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maruish</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editor. <source>The use of psychological testing for treatment planning and outcomes assessment.</source> <edition>3rd ed</edition>, vol <volume>3</volume>, <publisher-name>Instruments for adults</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>. p <fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schulberg</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saul</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McClelland</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ganguli</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christy</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing depression in primary medical and psychiatric practices</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry.</source> <year>1985</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1164</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Creamer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Biddle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The validity of the PTSD checklist as a measure of symptomatic change in combat-related PTSD</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Ther.</source> <year>2001</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>977</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilk</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riviere</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGurk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoge</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of mental health problems and functional impairment among active component and National Guard soldiers 3 and 12 months following combat in Iraq</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry.</source> <year>2010</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>614</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Von Korff</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ormel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keefe</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dworkin</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Grading the severity of chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Pain.</source> <year>1992</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Engelberg</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Swiontkowski</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Musculoskeletal function assessment: reference values for patient and non-patient samples</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res.</source> <year>1999</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hannaford</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The course of chronic pain in the community: results of a 4-year follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Pain.</source> <year>2002</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>1-2</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>307</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reiber</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McFarland</surname> <given-names>LV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blough</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gambel</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Servicemembers and veterans with major traumatic limb loss from Vietnam war and OIF/OEF conflicts: survey methods, participants, and summary findings</article-title>. <source>J Rehabil Res Dev.</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajewski</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Granville</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The United States Armed Forces Amputee Patient Care Program</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg.</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>10 Spec No</issue>.):<fpage>S183</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoge</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGurk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mild traumatic brain injury in U.S. soldiers returning from Iraq</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> <year>2008</year> <month>Jan</month> <day>31</day>;<volume>358</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>. <comment>Epub 2008 Jan 30</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grieger</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cozza</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ursano</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoge</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wain</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder and depression in battle-injured soldiers</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry.</source> <year>2006</year> <month>Oct</month>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1777</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>; <comment>quiz 1860</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Summary health statistics for U.S. adults: National Health Interview Survey, 2012</article-title>. <source>Vital Health Stat 10.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>260</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>LeardMann</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuna</surname> <given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyko</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blazer</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>; <collab>Millennium Cohort Study Team</collab>. <article-title>A prospective study of depression following combat deployment in support of the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health.</source> <year>2010</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pugh</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amuan</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brooke</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlini</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hadya</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ficke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bosse</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Selection bias in military cohort studies: an analysis of differences between participants and non-participants in a study of service members with severe limb trauma</article-title>. <source>Poster #055 2018 Military Health System Research Symposium</source>; <year>2018</year> <month>Aug</month> <day>20-23</day>; <publisher-loc>Kissimmee, FL</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eberlin</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ducic</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical algorithm for neuroma management: a changing treatment paradigm</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open.</source> <year>2018</year> <month>Oct</month> <day>16</day>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e1952</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuiken</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Targeted reinnervation for improved prosthetic function</article-title>. <source>Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am.</source> <year>2006</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cancio</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barnicott</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Childers</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alderete</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Upper extremity amputation and prosthetics care across the active duty military and veteran populations</article-title>. <source>Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am.</source> <year>2019</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>. <comment>Epub 2018 Oct 31</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>