<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns:r="http://www.rsuitecms.com/rsuite/ns/metadata" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" r:rsuiteId="1996476" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jbjsam</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Bone Joint Surg Am</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbjsam</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9355</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1535-1386</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JBJS-D-18-00660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.18.00660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>0170</subject><subject>0140</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Scientific Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effectiveness of a Flexible Locked Intramedullary Nail and an Anatomically Contoured Locked Plate to Treat Clavicular Shaft Fractures</article-title><subtitle>A 1-Year Randomized Control Trial</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9165-6205</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>Paul R.</given-names></name><degrees>MMed (Orth), FC(Orth)SA</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8719-9072</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikram</surname><given-names>Ajmal</given-names></name><degrees>MMed(Orth), FC(Orth)SA</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0623-2908</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Eken</surname><given-names>Maaike M.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1112-2604</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberts</surname><given-names>Robert P.</given-names></name><degrees>MSc, PHD, FECSS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Department of Surgical Studies, Stellenbosch University, Tygerberg, South Africa</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">E-mail address for R.P. Lamberts: <email>rplam@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><p><italic>Investigation performed at the Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Tygerberg Academic Hospital, and the Division of Orthopaedic Surgery, Department of Surgical Studies, Stellenbosch University, Tygerberg, South Africa</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2"><p><bold>Disclosure:</bold> The trial was funded with a grant from the South Africa Orthopaedic Association to compensate patients for travel costs. The <bold>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest</bold> forms are provided with the online version of the article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JBJS/F186">http://links.lww.com/JBJS/F186</ext-link>).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>101</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2019 by The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Incorporated</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="JBJS.18.00660.pdf" xlink:title="pdf"/><self-uri content-type="disclosure-pdf" xlink:href="JBJS.18.00660.disclosure.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Displaced and shortened clavicular shaft fractures can be treated operatively with intramedullary or extramedullary fixation. The aim of the present study was to compare the union rates and functional outcomes of displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fractures treated with a flexible locked intramedullary nail or with an anatomically contoured locked plate.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Seventy-two patients with acute displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fractures underwent randomly assigned management with either an intramedullary locked nail or an anatomically contoured locked plate. The same surgeon performed all surgical procedures, and all patients underwent identical postoperative treatment regimens. Incision length, surgical time, and union rate were recorded, and the functional outcome of the shoulder was assessed with use of the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) and Constant Shoulder (CS) scores. Data were analyzed with use of traditional statistical methods as well as Cohen effect sizes, which were based on the minimal clinical important differences.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Thirty-seven patients were managed with an anatomically contoured locked plate, and 35 patients were managed with a Sonoma CRx intramedullary flexible locked nail. There were no differences in general patient characteristics, fracture type, or displacement between treatment groups. The nailing group had significantly better outcomes (p &lt; 0.001) than the locked plating group for surgical time (mean and standard deviation [SD], 45 ± 12 compared with 65 ± 21 minutes, respectively) and incision size (mean and SD, 37 ± 9 compared with 116 ± 18 mm). A union rate of 100% was observed in both groups. DASH scores were similar between groups at 1.5, 3, and 6 months, whereas the nailing group had significantly better DASH scores at 12 months (p = 0.022); however, this difference had only a moderate effect size. Overall, individual variation in DASH and CS scores was substantially higher in the plating group compared with the nailing group.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Both the precontoured locked plate and the flexible locked intramedullary nail effectively treated displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fractures. Similar outcomes were achieved at 1.5, 3, and 6 months after surgical intervention, and better DASH scores were found in the nailing group at 12 months. Cohen effect sizes suggested that slightly better outcomes were potentially achieved in the nailing group.</p></sec><sec><title>Level of Evidence:</title><p>Therapeutic <underline>Level I</underline>. See Instructions for Authors for a complete description of levels of evidence.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Clavicular fractures are common, comprising 2.6% to 4.0% of all adult fractures and accounting for 35% of injuries to the shoulder girdle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup>. Recent studies have indicated higher complication rates in fracture types treated nonoperatively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2 bib3">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup>. In nonoperatively treated clavicular fractures, poorer outcomes have been associated with a higher degree of shortening<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup>. Compared with nonoperative treatment, operative treatment of displaced clavicular shaft fracture is associated with improved shoulder function, as measured with the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) and Constant Shoulder (CS) scores<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup>. In nonoperatively treated clavicles fractures, poorer outcome results have been associated with a higher degree of shortening<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup>. It is widely accepted that minimally displaced clavicular shaft fractures can and should be treated conservatively, with either a sling or a figure-of-8 bandage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup>. Operative treatment consists of open reduction and internal fixation involving locked or non-locked plates or involving intramedullary rods, wires, or nails<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup>. Numerous intramedullary fixation devices are available, including Knowles pins (Zimmer), Hagie pins (DePuy), Rockwood pins (DePuy), minimally invasive titanium nails (Synthes), and the Sonoma CRx nail (Sonoma Orthopedic Products)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p>Although several randomized controlled trials and systematic reviews have compared intramedullary nailing to traditional anatomical plating<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10 bib11">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup>, to our knowledge, no study to date has compared traditional plating with the use of the Sonoma CRx nail. In contrast with other nails, the Sonoma nail has a flexible medial part that allows the nail to follow the anatomical shape of the clavicle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>. After positioning the nail, the flexible part is made rigid with the use of an activation screw<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>. The lateral aspect of the device is locked with an interlocking screw and the medial aspect deploys grippers, providing rotational and length stability.</p><p>The aim of the present study was to compare the union rates and functional outcomes of displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fractures treated with a flexible locked intramedullary nail or with an anatomically contoured locked plate.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>This randomized controlled study compared the effectiveness of a flexible locked intramedullary nail with that of an anatomically contoured plate to restore union of the clavicle and the functional capacity of the shoulder in patients with a displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fracture.</p><p>Patients who had sustained a displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fracture between 2011 and 2013 and who sought treatment at the Division of Orthopaedic Surgery at the Tygerberg Academic Hospital were invited to participate in the study. Before enrollment, all patients signed an informed consent form, after which they were randomly assigned to either of the 2 treatment groups.</p><p>Ninety-two patients identified for inclusion in the study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Patients had to have been admitted to the hospital with a fracture of the shaft of the clavicle, as determined by the Allman classification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup>. In addition, the fracture had to be (1) shortened by ≥15 mm and/or (2) 100% displaced and/or comminuted. Patients with previous clavicular fractures or a pathological fracture were excluded from the study. A total of 5 patients were excluded from the study: 1 for not meeting inclusion criteria, 2 who declined to participate, and 2 who demanded a specific treatment and thus could not be randomized to a treatment group.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>CONSORT (Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials) flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="JBJS.18.00660f1"/></fig><p>With use of a computerized block randomization program, 42 patients were allocated to the nailing group and 45 patients were allocated to the plating group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). One patient in the nailing group did not receive the allocated intervention and was excluded from the study. During the study, 14 patients (6 in the nailing group and 8 in the plating group) were lost to follow-up, of whom 9 opted not to come back for follow-up assessments without providing a reason; these patients are marked as “unknown” in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>The primary outcomes of the study were the union rate and the functional shoulder capacity, as measured with the use of the DASH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> and CS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup> scores, at 1.5, 3, 6, and 12 months after the surgical procedure. In addition, surgical time, incision size, and rate of hardware failure were compared.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical Considerations</title><p>Ethical approval for this study was granted by the Health Research Ethics Committee of Stellenbosch University (M11/05/012;IRB0005239), and hospital clearance was given by Tygerberg Hospital. The principles outlined by the Declaration of Helsinki were followed.</p></sec><sec><title>Operative Treatment</title><p>Patients were assessed on admission and kept in a shoulder immobilizer until they underwent operative treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>. Fifteen-degree cephalad tilt radiographs were made at admission and used to classify fractures according to the Allman classification system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup>. The surgical preparation was similar for both groups, with patients being positioned in the beach chair position. Preoperatively, patients were administered 2 g of intravenous cefazolin and a general anesthetic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Anatomically Contoured Locked Plate</title><p>Patients in the anatomically contoured locked plating group were managed with the Acumed Clavicle Plating System. All plates were positioned superiorly, and the branches of the supraclavicular nerve were identified and protected during dissection. Care was taken not to disrupt the nerve branches while positioning the plate. Fractures were reduced, and fragments deemed large enough were fixed with interfragmentary lag screws. Small comminuted fragments were reduced and fixated with cerclage sutures. Closure of the wound was performed in layers, with care taken to approximate the detached muscle insertions over the plate and to approximate the platysma muscle as a separate layer.</p></sec><sec><title>Flexible Locked Intramedullary Nail</title><p>Patients allocated to the flexible locked intramedullary nailing group were managed with a Sonoma CRx intramedullary nail. This nail features a medial WaviBody assembly (Arthrex), which is a flexible portion that becomes rigid once activated. The nail is inserted into the medullary canal following reduction of the fracture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> with the flexible medial portion alongside the axial and coronal curvature of the clavicle. Following insertion and alignment along the clavicle, the WaviBody assembly is activated, becoming rigid and deploying grippers at the medial tip of the nail. These grippers, together with a lateral interlocking screw, secure the nail into place and prove length and rotational stability. A visual step-by-step process and description of the surgical technique involving the Sonoma nail has been previously published<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Rehabilitation and Data Capturing</title><p>The affected upper extremity was supported in a shoulder immobilizer for 6 weeks. Patients were advised to perform pendular exercises of the shoulder and flexion/extension exercises of the ipsilateral elbow 6 times a day for the 6-week period. Full range of movement exercises of the shoulder were commenced after 6 weeks. Full return to activity and contact sports were advised after 3 months<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Shoulder Function Assessments</title><p>Shoulder function was measured with use of DASH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> and CS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup> scores, with each patient being assessed by a single independent and experienced physiotherapist. The DASH system is a 30-item questionnaire quantifying physical function and symptoms of the upper limb<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>, with scores ranging from 0 (no disability) to 100 (completely disabled)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup>. CS scores are based on the flexion, abduction, internal and external rotation, and range of motion of the shoulder, with scores ranging from 0 (severe impairment) to 100 (no impairment)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup>. Union was determined by an independent radiologist on the basis of anteroposterior radiograph with a 15° cephalad tilt.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Size</title><p>An a priori sample size calculation was performed to determine the minimum sample size for this study. The sample size calculation was based on data from Gummesson et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> and the minimal clinically important difference (MCID) for DASH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref></sup> and CS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup> scores, which was set at 10 ± 13 points for both. To achieve a power of 80% with a significance level of 0.05, the sample size analyses indicated that 27 patients had to be allocated to each group. Based on potentially high drop-out rates, we aimed to recruit about 45 patients in each group.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Analysis</title><p>The data were analyzed with STATISTICA (version 13.3; TIBCO Software). Distribution and homogeneity of variances for the data were assessed with use of a Levene test. Differences in descriptive parametric parameters were analyzed with use of a t test, and nonparametric descriptive parameters were analyzed with use of a Mann-Whitney U test. DASH and CS scores were accepted as parametric data, which was in line with other randomized controlled trials<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup>. Differences over time (at 1.5, 3, 6, and 12 months), between treatment groups, and interaction effects (time × group), were analyzed with a repeated-measure analysis of variance test, with a Tukey post-hoc analysis when significance was found. Cohen effect sizes were calculated and determined as trivial (&lt;0.2), small (≥0.2 to &lt;0.5), moderate (≥0.5 to &lt;0.8), or large (≥0.8)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref></sup>. Significance was set at p &lt; 0.05.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial Registry</title><p>This study was registered in the public Pan African Clinical Trial Registry (PACTR201805003376209).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Of the 72 patients with a displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fracture who completed the study, 35 (49%) were managed with the precontoured locked plate and 37 (51%) with the flexible Sonoma CRx nail (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE I</label><caption><p>Patients Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plating Group (N = 37)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nailing Group (N = 35)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P Value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">General</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Age<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">*</xref> <italic>(yr)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 ± 12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 ± 14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.439</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Sex<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.991</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Male</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (54%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (74%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Female</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (46%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (26%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Injury details</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Fracture type<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">†</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Simple</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (65%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (66%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0985</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Single fragment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (5%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (9%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.773</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Multiple fragments</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (30%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (26%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.983</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Coronal displacement<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">*</xref> <italic>(mm)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 ± 9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 ± 13</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.186</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Shortening<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">*</xref> <italic>(mm)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 ± 9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 ± 10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.970</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Surgical details</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Surgical time<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">*</xref> <italic>(min)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 ± 21</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 ± 12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Incision length<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">*</xref> <italic>(mm)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">116 ± 18</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 ± 9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>*</label><p>Data are presented as the mean and SD.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>†</label><p>Data are presented as the number of patients with the percentage of patients in the cohort in parentheses.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Although no differences were found in the general characteristics, the nailing group had significantly better outcomes than the locked plating group for surgical time (mean and standard deviation [SD], 45 ± 12 compared with 65 ± 21 minutes) and incision size (mean and SD, 37 ± 9 compared with 116 ± 18 mm; p &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). At 12 months, a union rate of 100% was observed in both the anatomically contoured locked plating group and the locked intramedullary nailing group.</p><p>The nailing group had significantly better DASH scores at 12 months (p = 0.022), whereas scores were similar between groups at 1.5, 3, and 6 months (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). However, only small to moderate Cohen effect sizes were found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Interestingly, 2 patients in the plating group had a worse DASH score at 12 months than at 6 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE II</label><caption><p>Changes in Functional Outcome Scores at 1.5, 3, 6, and 12 Months Postoperatively</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Plating Group<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">*</xref> <italic>(points)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nailing Group<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">*</xref> <italic>(points)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean Difference between the Plating and Nailing Group <italic>(Points)</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P Value</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohen Effect Size<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">†</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cohen Effect Size – Magnitude Descriptor</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DASH<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn5">‡</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.5 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 ± 24</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 ± 15</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.590</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32 (−0.12 to 0.76)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Small</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 ± 17</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 ± 12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.670</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.37 (−0.02 to 0.75)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Small</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 6 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 ± 16</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 ± 6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.419</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57 (0.18 to 0.96)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 12 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 ± 19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 ± 6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.022<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn6">§</xref></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70 (0.29 to 1.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CS<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn5">‡</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 1.5 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 ± 21</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 ± 14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.091</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61 (0.17 to 1.06)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 ± 19</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 ± 7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.107</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56 (0.21 to 0.91)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 6 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 ± 16</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 ± 6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.173</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64 (0.25 to 1.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 12 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 ± 12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 ± 5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.612</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57 (0.13 to 1.01)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><label>*</label><p>Data are presented as the mean and SD.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>†</label><p>Data are presented as the mean with the 95% confidence interval in parentheses; positive values reflect a better effect size in nailing and negative values reflect a better effect size in plating.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><label>‡</label><p>The MCID was 10.85 for DASH scores and 10.4 for CS scores<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup>.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn6"><label>§</label><p>Significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>DASH and CS scores at 1.5, 3, 6, and 12 months after surgical intervention in the plating (blue circles) and nailing (red circles) groups, with mean ± standard deviation (<bold>Fig. 2-A</bold>) and individual (<bold>Fig. 2-B</bold>) CS scores and mean ± standard deviation (<bold>Fig. 2-C</bold>) and individual (<bold>Fig. 2-D</bold>) DASH scores. *P &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="JBJS.18.00660f2"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Overview of the DASH and CS Cohen effect sizes. Data are presented as the mean with 95% confidence intervals.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="JBJS.18.00660f3"/></fig><sec><title>Complications</title><p>One patient in each group was treated with oral antibiotics for superficial wound infections. Hardware failure was also observed in 1 patient from each group. One patient in the nailing group, who resumed hard physical work directly after the operation against the postoperative treatment regimen, was diagnosed with hardware failure at the junction of the flexible and the rigid part of the nail. In 1 patient in the plating group, the screws of the lateral fragment of the plate were pulled out as a result of a fall in the shower; the plate was removed, but the patient declined any other further treatment to correct the malunion. Except for this removal, no other anatomical plates or intramedullary nails were surgically removed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present randomized controlled trial aimed to compare the treatment of displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fractures with either an anatomically contoured locked plate or a flexible intramedullary nail that is locked into position with medial grippers and a lateral interlocking screw. Patients were well randomized, as the age, gender, and fracture types were similar both groups; however, surgical time and incision size differed by a factor of 1.4 and 3.1, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). Treatment with both the anatomically contoured locked plate as well as the locked intramedullary nail resulted in a 100% union rate. Differences in shoulder function, as measured by DASH and CS scores, were assessed with use of traditional statistical methods as well as the Cohen effect size to determine the likelihood that these differences were clinically meaningful. Similar DASH and CS results were observed in the nailing and plating groups except at 12 months, at which point the mean DASH score was slightly better in the nailing group (p = 0.022). However, only a moderate Cohen effect size was observed. In addition, individual data plots show that 2 patients in the plating group had substantially worse DASH scores at 12 months compared with 6 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2-D</xref>). Although no clear reason for this worsening could be found, excluding these points from the data set resulted in no longer finding a difference between the plating and nailing group for DASH scores at 12 months (p = 0.151), which supports the finding that this difference might not be clinically relevant.</p><p>The DASH and CS scores observed in the plating group are in line with those of studies involving similar<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> and/or the same plate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup>. DASH and CS scores reported in the flexible nail group of the present study tended to be higher than those reported in rigid nails or pins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24 bib25 bib26">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup>. Whereas we observed a mean CS score of 97, Ferran et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup>, Liu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup>, and Lee et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> reported scores of 92, 86, and 95, respectively, with use of a Rockford nail, a titanium elastic nail, and a Knowles pin, respectively.</p><p>Similar to the present study, Calbiyik et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> compared the use of a locking compression plate with the Sonoma CRx nail to treat clavicular fractures. In that study, a different surgical technique involving a medial entry point lateral to the sternoclavicular joint was utilized, rather than the standard lateral entry point utilized in the present study. In line with our study, Calbiyik et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> reported better DASH scores in the nailing group; however, the main limitation of that study was that patients did not undergo a standardized follow-up period (e.g. 12 months) but were assessed after “at least 12 months,” which might have influenced the findings. In contrast, Zehir et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup> found no differences in QuickDASH (an abbreviated version of the DASH questionnaire) scores between patients managed with a minimally invasive locking superior plate or with the Sonoma CRx nail; however, the difference in follow-up time between the plating (14.5 months) and nailing group (11.8 months) might have influenced those findings.</p><p>In the present study, hardware failure was minimal in both groups and could be related to extreme circumstances in both cases. Nail migration traditionally has been a problem and has resulted in a high rate of hardware removal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup>. However, with use of modern nails such as the Sonoma nail, these hardware problems no longer seem to be a major problem<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup>, and no signs of hardware migration in the nailing group were observed in the present study.</p><p>The limitations of the present study are that the randomized controlled trial was not a multicenter study and that all surgical procedures were performed by the same surgeon, who was experienced using both devices. Although the use of a single surgeon could be a confounding factor, it also minimizes the variation in surgical technique that exists between surgeons. Because the surgeon in the present study had extensive experience implanting the nail, other surgeons who are less familiar with the hardware might experience slightly longer surgical times. Lastly, although the medial part of the flexible nail becomes rigid after activation, it is likely not as strong as a 1-piece intramedullary nail, which can lead to hardware failure. However, the relatively low number of hardware failures reported in this device suggests that it is sufficiently strong<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p>In conclusion, both the Acumed precontoured locked plate and the Sonoma CRx intramedullary nail effectively treated displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fracture, resulting in a union rate of 100% in both groups. Similar DASH and CS scores were observed at 1.5, 3, and 6 months. DASH scores at 12 months were better in the nailing group, although individual responses indicate that this finding might not be clinically meaningful. However, better DASH and CS Cohen effect sizes (small to moderate) were found in the nailing group. Overall, we conclude that both devices can be used to effectively treat displaced and/or shortened clavicular shaft fracture. Factors such as preference, surgical skill, and cosmetic result are likely to influence the decision of the treating surgeon.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bradnock</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fractures of the clavicle</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2009</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zlowodzki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zelle</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeray</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKee</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></string-name></person-group>; <article-title>Evidence-Based Orthopaedic Trauma Working Group. Treatment of acute midshaft clavicle fractures: systematic review of 2144 fractures: on behalf of the Evidence-Based Orthopaedic Trauma Working Group</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma.</source> <year>2005</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>504</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crosby</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Closed treatment of displaced middle-third fractures of the clavicle gives poor results</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br.</source> <year>1997</year> <month>Jul</month>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>537</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Böhme</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bacher</surname> <given-names>GO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilharm</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Josten</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>[Current treatment concepts for mid-shaft fractures of the clavicle - results of a prospective multicentre study]. [German.]</article-title>. <source>Z Orthop Unfall.</source> <year>2011</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>. Epub 2010 Oct 12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarides</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zafiropoulos</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Conservative treatment of fractures at the middle third of the clavicle: the relevance of shortening and clinical outcome</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg.</source> <year>2006</year> <month>Mar-Apr</month>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eskola</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vainionpää</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pätiälä</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rokkanen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Outcome of operative treatment in fresh lateral clavicular fracture</article-title>. <source>Ann Chir Gynaecol.</source> <year>1987</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Canadian Orthopaedic Trauma Society</collab>. <article-title>Nonoperative treatment compared with plate fixation of displaced midshaft clavicular fractures. A multicenter, randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2007</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jubel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andermahr</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schiffer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsironis</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Elastic stable intramedullary nailing of midclavicular fractures with a titanium nail</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res.</source> <year>2003</year> <month>Mar</month>;(<volume>408</volume>):<fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ikram</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberts</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The treatment of clavicular shaft fractures with an innovative locked intramedullary device</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg.</source> <year>2015</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. Epub 2014 Jun 18.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Houwert</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wijdicks</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Steins Bisschop</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verleisdonk</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kruyt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Plate fixation versus intramedullary fixation for displaced mid-shaft clavicle fractures: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int Orthop.</source> <year>2012</year> <month>Mar</month>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>. Epub 2011 Dec 7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wijdicks</surname> <given-names>FJG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Houwert</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Millett</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verleisdonk</surname> <given-names>EJJM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Meijden</surname> <given-names>OAJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review of complications after intramedullary fixation for displaced midshaft clavicle fractures</article-title>. <source>Can J Surg.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>van der Meijden</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Houwert</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hulsmans</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wijdicks</surname> <given-names>FJG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkgraaf</surname> <given-names>MGW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meylaerts</surname> <given-names>SAG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hammacher</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verhofstad</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verleisdonk</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Operative treatment of dislocated midshaft clavicular fractures: plate or intramedullary nail fixation? A randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2015</year> <month>Apr</month> <day>15</day>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Basamania</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberts</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A novel intramedullary locked fixation device for treatment of clavicle shaft fractures</article-title>. <source>JBJS Essent Surg Tech.</source> <year>2016</year> <month>Feb</month> <day>24</day>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e8</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Allman</surname> <given-names>FL</given-names> <suffix>Jr.</suffix></string-name></person-group> <article-title>Fractures and ligamentous injuries of the clavicle and its articulation</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>1967</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>774</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hudak</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amadio</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bombardier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>; <article-title>The Upper Extremity Collaborative Group (UECG). Development of an upper extremity outcome measure: the DASH (disabilities of the arm, shoulder and hand) [corrected] [corrected]</article-title>. <source>Am J Ind Med.</source> <year>1996</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>602</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Constant</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murley</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A clinical method of functional assessment of the shoulder</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res.</source> <year>1987</year> <month>Jan</month>;(<issue>214</issue>):<fpage>160</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gummesson</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Atroshi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ekdahl</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The disabilities of the arm, shoulder and hand (DASH) outcome questionnaire: longitudinal construct validity and measuring self-rated health change after surgery</article-title>. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord.</source> <year>2003</year> <month>Jun</month> <day>16</day>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>. Epub 2003 Jun 16.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Franchignoni</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vercelli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sartorio</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bravini</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferriero</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Minimal clinically important difference of the disabilities of the arm, shoulder and hand outcome measure (DASH) and its shortened version (QuickDASH)</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther.</source> <year>2014</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. Epub 2013 Oct 30.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kukkonen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kauko</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vahlberg</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joukainen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aärimaa</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigating minimal clinically important difference for Constant score in patients undergoing rotator cuff surgery</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg.</source> <year>2013</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1650</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>. Epub 2013 Jul 12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tamaoki</surname> <given-names>MJS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matsunaga</surname> <given-names>FT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>ARFD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Netto</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belloti</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of displaced midshaft clavicle fractures: figure-of-eight harness versus anterior plate osteosynthesis: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2017</year> <month>Jul</month> <day>19</day>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1159</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woltz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stegeman</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krijnen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Dijkman</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Thiel</surname> <given-names>TPH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schep</surname> <given-names>NWL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Rijcke</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frölke</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schipper</surname> <given-names>IB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Plate fixation compared with nonoperative treatment for displaced midshaft clavicular fractures: a multicenter randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am.</source> <year>2017</year> <month>Jan</month> <day>18</day>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> <source>Statistical power analysis for behavioral science.</source> <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Earlbaum Associates.</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Plating versus intramedullary fixation for mid-shaft clavicle fractures: a systemic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>PeerJ.</source> <year>2016</year> <month>Feb</month> <day>22</day>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1540</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Calbiyik</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ipek</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taskoparan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective randomized study comparing results of fixation for clavicular shaft fractures with intramedullary nail or locking compression plate</article-title>. <source>Int Orthop.</source> <year>2017</year> <month>Jan</month>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. Epub 2016 May 2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferran</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vannet</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>RO</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Locked intramedullary fixation vs plating for displaced and shortened mid-shaft clavicle fractures: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg.</source> <year>2010</year> <month>Sep</month>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>783</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chia</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tarng</surname> <given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of plates versus intramedullary nails for fixation of displaced midshaft clavicular fractures</article-title>. <source>J Trauma.</source> <year>2010</year> <month>Dec</month>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>E82</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname> <given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname> <given-names>YF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical treatment of midclavicular fractures: a prospective comparison of Knowles pinning and plate fixation</article-title>. <source>Int Orthop.</source> <year>2008</year> <month>Aug</month>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>. Epub 2007 Mar 16.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zehir</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zehir</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Şahin</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Çalbıyık</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of novel intramedullary nailing with mini-invasive plating in surgical fixation of displaced midshaft clavicle fractures</article-title>. <source>Arch Orthop Trauma Surg.</source> <year>2015</year> <month>Mar</month>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>. Epub 2015 Jan 1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smekal</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Irenberger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Struve</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wambacher</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krappinger</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kralinger</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Elastic stable intramedullary nailing versus nonoperative treatment of displaced midshaft clavicular fractures-a randomized, controlled, clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma.</source> <year>2009</year> <month>Feb</month>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>-12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kettler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schieker</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Braunstein</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>König</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mutschler</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Flexible intramedullary nailing for stabilization of displaced midshaft clavicle fractures: technique and results in 87 patients</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop.</source> <year>2007</year> <month>Jun</month>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>424</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>